Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00756
Sophia Smith Collection
- JD Samson interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 January 6; Samson, JD, 1978-; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  - Video interview of JD Samson
  - Transcript of interview of JD Samson
- Patty Schemel interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 August 17; Schemel, Patty, 1967-; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Patty Schemel discusses her upbringing in Marysville, WA., her relationship with her parents and siblings, her early musical influences and interest in the drums. She details her experience in school, with her peers, and how she came out to her mother. Schemel offers insight into the Seattle music scene and discusses her single minded approach to turning drums into a career. She discusses her move to CA, where she joined Hole, and her trajectory to rock stardom, descent into drug addiction, and how she eventually overcame those obstacles. Schemel also talks at length about women's place in rock history, her involvement in Girls Rock camps, relationships with friends and colleagues, becoming a parent, and coming to terms with her her identity as a gay woman and recovering addict.
  Patty Schemel is a musician, drummer, who rose to prominence as a member of the rock band Hole. Schemel continues to play music in the band Upset, volunteers at Girls Rock Camp and gives drum lessons, in addition to owning a dog daycare/boarding business. She lives in Los Angeles with her wife and daughter.
  Schemel, Patty, 1967-
  - Video interview of Patty Schemel
- Azalia Snail interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2017 August 25; Snail, Azalia; Pearson, Tanya
  In this oral history, Azalia Snail discusses her childhood and upbringing in Newark, NJ, her beatnik parents, early musical influences and the pivotal moment when she discovered electric guitar. She details her difficult teenage years, being an outcast, and her eventual move to NYC. Snail talks about her writing process, touring, the recording process, relationships, and how she became the "Queen of LoFi" in the 1990s. The interview closes with her thoughts on gender and the visibility of women in rock history.
  Snail, Azalia
  - Video interview of Azalia Snail
- Donita Sparks interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 July 21; Sparks, Donita; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history, Donita Sparks discusses her upbringing in Chicago, including hobbies, interests, family and her introduction to rock music. She speaks candidly about her move to Los Angeles after high school, the music scene there and the space she occupied within it. Sparks details the formation of L7, the bands success, subsequent dissolution and current reunion. She addresses her feminism, women's contributions to rock music and her opinion regarding the Women of Rock category.
  This interview is currently not available for research.
  Sparks, Donita
  - Video interview of Donita Sparks
  - Transcript of interview of Donita Sparks
- Mary Timony interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2014 December 28; Timony, Mary; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history, Mary Timony discusses her childhood in Washington, D.C. and her interest in music from a young age. She details her high school and college experience, including the music scene in Washington, D.C. in the early 1990s and how her participation in the musical community helped to curb her social anxiety. Timony recalls her college career, the formation of her band, Helium, and what led to their disbandment. She discusses her musical output, collaborations, relationships and some of the double standards that women rock musicians face.
  Mary Timony (b. 1970) is a multi-instrumentalist who founded the band Autoclave in Washington D.C. and gained greater recognition as singer and guitarist in the Boston, Massachusetts band, Helium in the mid 1990s. Timony has released two solo albums and collaborated with a number of musicians on outside projects throughout her career. In 2011, she formed Wild Flag with members of Sleater Kinney and released an album before forming the critically acclaimed Ex Hex in 2014. When she's not touring, Timony teaches guitar lessons in Washington, D.C.
  Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrator until 2055: .52-1:44; 19:54-20:50; 52:50-53.44. Edited versions of the transcript and video are available for research use. This interview may not be placed online.
  Timony, Mary
  - Unredacted video interview of Mary Timony
    Portions of this interview are restricted by the narrator. A redacted version is available for research use in-house only.
  - Redacted video interview of Mary Timony
    Portions of this interview are restricted by the narrator. This redacted version is available for research use in-house only.
  - Unredacted transcript of interview of Mary Timony
    The unredacted version of this interview is closed. A redacted version is available for research use.
  - Redacted transcript of interview of Mary Timony
- Veruca Salt (Nina Gordon and Louise Post) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 January 12; Gordon, Nina, 1967-; Post, Louise; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history Nina Gordon and Louise Post discuss their early lives and the fortuitous meeting that led to the formation of Veruca Salt. The interview focuses on their personal experiences within the band, as successful female musicians in the mid to late 1990s, the difficulties that led to their 17-year estrangement, and the events that led to their subsequent reunion.
  Nina Gordon (b. 1967) and Louise Post (b. 1966) are vocalists and guitarists of the rock band, Veruca Salt. Co-founded in 1993, the band reached critical and commercial success in 1994 with the release of their first album American Thighs. The band signed to Geffen Records and gained popularity when the single "Seether" became a hit. After releasing the EP Blow it Out Your Ass, It's Veruca Salt (1996) and a second full-length album, Eight Arms to Hold You (1997), Gordon left the band and embarked on a brief solo career and Post recorded two more albums and an EP under the Veruca Salt moniker. In 2014, the original lineup reunited and toured the United States and Australia. Their first album in 17 years, Ghost Notes, was released in July 2015.
  Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrators: 46:45-47:10; 1:46:38-1:54:28. A redacted version is available for research use.
  Veruca Salt (Musical group); Post, Louise; Gordon, Nina, 1967-
  - Unredacted video interview of Veruca Salt
    The unredacted version of this interview is closed. A redacted version is available for research use in-house.
  - Redacted video interview of Veruca Salt
    Portions of this interview are restricted by the narrators. This redacted version is available for research use in-house.
  - Unredacted transcript of interview with Veruca Salt
  - Redacted transcript of interview of Veruca Salt
    Portions of this interview are restricted by the narrators. This redacted version is available for research use.
- Josephine Wiggs interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2017 July 23; Wiggs, Josephine, 1963-; 1 items (1 video file)
  Wiggs, Josephine, 1963-
  - Video interview of Josephine Wiggs
- Allison Wolfe interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 August 17; Pearson, Tanya; Wolfe, Allison; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  Wolfe, Allison
  - Video interview of Allison Wolfe
- "Righting the Wrongs of Rock History: Women, Gender and Rock" (panel discussion), 2015 Oct 22; 2015-s-0083_part 02; 1.38 Gigabytes 1. 38 GB (26 images, 1 video)
  A panel discussion held at Smith College, October, 22, 2015, introducing the first known oral history project about female rock & rollers. Panelists (from left): Julie Cafritz, JD Samson, Kristen Hersh, Alice Bag, Kim House, and June Millington; moderated by Tanya Pearson with an introduction by Kelly Anderson.
  Tanya Pearson (Smith Class 2016) conducted the Women of Rock Oral History Project for her Archives Concentration Capstone Project and honors thesis. She has donated the interviews (video recordings and transcripts) to the Sophia Smith Collection.
  Video and images are open for research with no restrictions.
  - Video of Women of Rock panel
  - Images of Women of Rock panel